A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Ted Smith FA1529
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Ted Smith
1964-1976, bulk 1972-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
Smith, Theodore M.
Ford Foundation
FA1529
7.57 Cubic Feet 12 LTR, 1 half-LTR, and 6 LGL size Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the staff subject files of Ted Smith (Theodore M. Smith) who worked at the Ford Foundation from between 1967 and 1979. Although Smith was primarily associated with the Jakarta, Indonesia Regional Office during his tenure at Ford, the collection so far consists only of the files Smith created during the course of his work on two other projects. First, between 1973 and 1974, he assisted Francis Sutton in reviewing the Foundation's support of public management initiatives in developing countries. Then, between 1974 and 1976, he worked on the Foundation budget under President McGeorge Bundy. Nevertheless, there is some correspondence in the collection that discusses a period of time between 1974 and 1975 where Smith returned to Indonesia at the request of the Indonesian government in order to assist the National Family Planning Coordinating Board.
The collection primarily consists of correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, papers, agendas, data tables, meeting minutes and summaries, expense reports, publications, and Recommended Grant Action records (RGAs).
The collection is made up of more than one accession of Ted Smith subject files. The records were transferred to the RAC in two different batches (Accession 2019:033 and Accession 2019:047) but were processed into the same collection in order to represent their contextual relationship.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation in two different batches. The records were ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2019:033 and 2019:047.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of one series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible. Records from the two accessions (Accession 2019:033 and 2019:047) were processed into the collection at the same time in relation to the sequential order of the original box numbers.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1964-1976, bulk 1972-1976
Biographical / Historical
Ted Smith (Theodore M. Smith) (1942-2012) was a philanthropist and conservationist who served for 12 years at the Ford Foundation. During his tenure at Ford, Smith worked primarily with the Jakarta, Indonesia Regional Office. Between 1967 and 1973, he moved from Assistant to the Representative, to Assistant Representative, and then to Acting Representative for Indonesia. He left his work with the Jakarta Office in order to support two different projects in the mid-1970s. As Project Specialist in Public Management between 1973 and 1974, he assisted Francis Sutton in reviewing the Foundation's support of public management initiatives in developing countries. He then served as Assistant to the President between 1974 and 1976. In this position, he was responsible for working with Ford Foundation President McGeorge Bundy on the Foundation's budget. This occurred during the period in the Foundation's history when its assets were depreciated and its leadership sought to determine if and how it should continue to operate in future years. After completing that assignment, Smith returned to working with the Jakarta Office as Representative for Indonesia and remained in that post until he left the foundation in 1979.
Smith received a BA in Government from Pomona College in 1963 and then a MA in Political Science and a PhD in Cooperative Administration from the University of California, Berkeley in 1964 and 1971 respectively. During his summers in college, Smith worked as a smokejumper for the United States Forest Department in Missoula, Montana.
After leaving the Ford Foundation in 1979, Smith continued to work in philanthropy and began focusing more on natural conservation concerns. He was President of the Agricultural Development Council, founding Executive Director of the Consultative Group on Biological Diversity, and Executive Director of the Kendall Foundation. Smith was also a member of the Alaska Conservation Foundation's Board of Trustees.
Ford Foundation; Africa; Asia; Economic development; Family planning; Government business enterprises -- Reform -- Africa; Indonesia; Latin America; Middle East; Program budgeting; Public administration
- Subject files, 1964-1976, bulk 1972-1976; 1; 7.57 Cubic Feet 12 LTR, 1 half-LTR, and 6 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Files in the series primarily regard the two main projects that Ted Smith worked on during the mid-1970s. Correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, papers, meeting minutes, newspaper clippings, and data tables document Smith's work on the Ford Foundation budget as Assistant to the President between 1974 and 1976. These documents chiefly regard the Foundation's financial condition, program budget projections, program prioritizing and planning, meetings and communications to the Board of Trustees and Program Officers, and internal studies conducted by the Planning Agenda Task Forces and Advisory Committees. Most of the other files within the series regard Smith's work on the International Division's Public Management Review between 1973 and 1974. These materials document Smith's assistance to Frank Sutton in preparing a report on the Ford Foundation's support of public management initiatives in developing countries in Asia, Africa, the Middle East, and Latin America. As part of this work, Smith helped organize seminars in countries like India, Indonesia, Ghana, and Peru for Foundation staff to discuss the state of public management, the Foundation's record in supporting public management development, and the level of interest the Foundation should take in improving public management within the context of those different nations. He collaborated with the various Foundation field offices in order to better understand how the Foundation had engaged with public management efforts in different countries, and he also supported consultants who studied public management related topics such as the role of public corporations in developing countries.
  While the files pertaining to Smith's work on the Ford Foundation budget are primarily located at the front of the series, documents concerning the two different projects are somewhat intermingled.
  There is a small amount of correspondence within the series that provides insight into Smith's activities outside of his work on the Ford Foundation budget and the Public Management Review. Some letters in the Trip and Chronological files regard Smith's brief returns to Indonesia in order to assist the National Family Planning Coordinating Board in 1974 and 1975. Documents also allude to Smith's permanent return to the Jakarta Office as Indonesia Representative after the conclusion of his stint as Assistant to the President in 1976.
  - Budget revisions, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    File subheadings include:
    Education and Research
    Humanities and the Arts
    National Affairs
    International Division – General
    International Division – Middle East and Africa
    Population
    Public Broadcasting
    Resources and the Environment
    Program Related Investments
  - Overhang/Division Planning Papers/Trustee concerns, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Budget papers, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Overhang
    Division Planning Papers
    Transition
    Public Relations
    Forward Planning Meeting
    General Budget
  - Budget, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fiscal Year 1976-1977 program budgets, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
    Humanities and Arts
    International Division – Office of Latin America and the Caribbean
    International Division – European and International Affairs
    International Division – Asia and Pacific
    Resources and Environment
    Program Related Investments/New York City/Michigan
  - Budget revisions, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - A Further Look at Program/Budget Alternatives memo/Other program/budget planning memos and meeting minutes, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - International Division Planning Paper (A Further Look at Program/Budget Alternatives), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - June 13, 1974 Planning Session (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Office of Resources and Environment Planning Paper, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Education and Research Division Planning Paper, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Administration Planning Paper, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Excluded Alternatives draft, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Memos about budget and programming, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - National Affairs Division Planning Paper, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Public Broadcasting Planning Paper, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Program Choices, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Proposed Revisions in 1975 Program Budget and Preliminary Presentations of 2-Year Program Budgets for Fiscal Year 1976 and 1977, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Humanities and the Arts Division Planning Paper, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - McGeorge Bundy memo to Trustees, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Retrenchment of program management costs, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Preliminary Budget Planning for Fiscal Year 1974 and Fiscal Year 1975 Discussion Paper, 1973 March (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Internal Internship Program, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 31-32)
  - Task Force on Learning, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Future Program - Division of Education and Research drafts, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - General - Planning Agenda Task Forces and Advisory Committees, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Study on individual awards, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - General Reserve, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Small Program Actions, 1967-1975 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Women, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
  - Press clippings about financial condition, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Size and number of grants - Workload, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Workload study, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - American Society for Public Administration (ASPA) Section on International and Comparative Administration (SICA) Newsletter, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Program of Advanced Studies in Institution Building and Technical Assistance Methodologies (PASITAM), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Seminar on Indonesian Development, Indonesia Embassy, Washington D.C., 1975 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs Meeting, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 47-48)
  - Bureaucratic productivity, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Development administration, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 50-52)
  - Grants in Development Planning and Management, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 53-54)
  - Eastern Bloc management, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Ford Foundation management - Personnel, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Ford Foundation Program in Public Management - East and Southern Africa Conference, Dar es Salaam, Tanzania, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Latin America - Public management, 1971-1973 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - International Institute of Administrative Sciences (IIAS), 1971-1973 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Management consulting, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 60-61)
  - Management - General, 1964-1974 (Box 7, Folder 62-64)
  - Management - General, 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 65-67)
  - Administrative reform, 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 68-69)
  - Africa - Public management, 1968-1975 (Box 9, Folder 70-74)
  - Africa - Public management, 1968-1973 (Box 10, Folder 75-80)
  - Asia - Public management, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 81-85)
  - Delegated Authority Project (DAP) for Review of Problems in Public Management, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 86)
  - Report by the Auditor-General on the Accounts of Ghana, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Rolodex cards, undated (Box 12, Folder 88-89)
  - Financial memos, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Affirmative action, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Chronological file, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - Trustees' Review, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 93)
  - Pending, 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 94)
  - Resume, 1974-1975 (Box 12, Folder 95)
  - Public Management Review - Final Report distribution, undated (Box 12, Folder 96)
  - Budget memos and drafts distribution - Office of the President, circa 1975 (Box 12, Folder 97)
  - Personnel policies, 1973-1974 (Box 12, Folder 98)
  - Paul Strasburg and Frederick Bowhen files requests, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 99)
  - Leveraging money paper, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs, 1974-1975 (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - New program ideas, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - Public Management Review distribution, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - Harvard Institute for International Development (HIID) review, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 104)
  - Human rights, 1973-1976 (Box 12, Folder 105)
  - Coordinating Committee on Women's Programs report, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 106)
  - Questions at Officers' Meetings, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - Foundation for Educational Experimentation in Indonesia (FEEI), 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 108)
  - Transition draft memos, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 109)
  - Warren Ilchman - Population policy seminar, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Harvard University trips, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 111)
  - Washington D.C. trips, undated (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Middle East trip, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University grant, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - Ted Smith memos and other papers, 1973-1975 (Box 13, Folder 115)
  - Robert W. Kerwin - A Management Consultancy and Training Strategy for Public Management paper, undated (Box 13, Folder 116)
  - Clifford Geertz - Report to the Ford Foundation Concerning a Program for the Stimulation of the Social Sciences in Indonesia paper, 1971 August (Box 13, Folder 117)
  - International Division travel schedules, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 118)
  - University of Connecticut trip, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 119)
  - June Trustees' Meeting, 1974 April 24 (Box 13, Folder 120)
  - London, England trip, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 121)
  - Washington D.C. trip, 1972-1974 (Box 14, Folder 122)
  - Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs, Syracuse University Recommended Grant Action (RGA), 1973 (Box 14, Folder 123)
  - Merrimon Cuninggim reports, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Charles Waigi expense reports, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - Charles Waigi - Public Corporations: Management Problems in Tanzania, Kenya, and Ghana drafts, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 126-127)
  - Public corporations, 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 128-129)
  - Public enterprise, 1970-1975 (Box 15, Folder 130-134)
  - Public management Recommended Grant Actions (RGAs), 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 135)
  - Public enterprise, 1968-1974 (Box 16, Folder 136-140)
  - Public Management Review notes, 1968-1975 (Box 16, Folder 141-142)
  - Public Management Review - Francis Sutton memo to Overseas Representatives, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 143)
  - Public Management Review questionnaire responses, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 144)
  - Public Management Review questionnaire responses, 1970-1974 (Box 17, Folder 145-146)
  - Trips, 1973-1975 (Box 17, Folder 147-148)
    London trip
    Mid-East trip
    Indonesia - As Acting Representative
    Indonesia 1975
    Indonesia 1974
    Peru/Brazil
  - Chronological file, 1975-1976 (Box 17, Folder 149-150)
    International Executive Service Corps (IESC)
    Association for Asian Studies - Indonesia Committee
    Memos to McGeorge Bundy
  - Public management seminars, 1973-1975 (Box 18, Folder 151)
  - Public management consultants, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 152)
    Robert W. Kerwin correspondence
    Charles Waigi
  - Chronological file, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 153-154)
  - Chronological file, 1973-1975 (Box 18, Folder 155-157)
    General
    Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs
  - Public management seminar - Eastern Bloc, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 158)
  - Public management seminar - Ghana, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 159)
  - Public enterprises seminar - Harvard University, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 160)
  - Population policy seminar - Ilchman, Warren, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 161)
  - Public management seminar - India, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 162)
  - Public management seminar - Indonesia, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 163)
  - Public management seminar - Peru, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 164)
  - Public Management Review budget, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 165)